[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at
SE-R SE radio is brought to you by the
it computer society and by It software
Magazine online at computer.org
[Music]
software welcome to software engineering
radio this is Philip Winston I'm here
today with Maxim faiv Maxim is the
co-founder and CEO of temporal he has
worked in lead roles at Amazon micro
roft Google and Uber he led the
development of AWS simple workflow
service at Amazon and the op Source
Cadence workflow at Uber Maxum holds
degrees in computer science and physics
we're going to talk today about
automating business processes with
distributed systems but let's start with
a term not everyone might be familiar
with durable execution Maxim what is a
durable execution and why is it a useful
abstraction durable execution is a new
abstraction which we kind of introduced
and it's not very well known but I think
every engineer absolutely should have it
in their back pocket of tools the idea
is pretty straightforward imagine
runtime which keeps the full state of
your code execution durable all the time
it means that if process crashes or any
other infrastructure outage happens like
Network event power outage and so on
your code will keep running after the
problem is resolved or if it's process
CR it just will be migrated to a
separate process but if the whole region
is down as soon as it comes back your
code will continue executing and I'm not
saying process but actually the full
state so for example if you have a
function which is blocked like executes
let's say three API calls A B C and it's
blocked on B and then this process
crashes this execution will migrate to
another machine and it will be still
blocked on B and B result can come two
days later and then it will continue
executing so all local variables in the
whole state including block and calls is
fully preserved all the time great we're
definitely going to get into how that
works but before we do that we're going
to do a little bit of history and how we
got here but let's just describe
temporal as it exists today so temporal
is an open source project it's MIT
licensed so you can absolutely run it
yourself including both his DK libraries
and the backend server which keeps the
state and so this project we started at
tuber it was initially called Cadence
and then four years ago we started a
company with fork the project and we
call it temporal and it's been around
for seven years in production at high
scale and used by thousands of companies
around the world for Mission critical
applications let's go back even further
before Cadence you worked on the simple
workflow service at Amazon can you tell
me a little bit about how that project
started and what were the goals of the
project so I probably want to start even
earlier I joined Amazon first time in
2002 and back then Amazon was actively
moving from monolith architecture to
micro service architecture it wasn't
called microservices back then it was
called just Services later it was called
saw but basic idea was the same that
this monolith was unsustainable just
relinking that binary was taking 45
minutes on a high-end desktop so it
wasn't practical to do any development
so Amazon had to do that and we found
that practically we used the standard
approach even back then of using cues to
connect multiple Services together and
practically execute all this backend
business processes and I was Tech lead
for the pop sub group I practically was
leading Group which was owning all
backend pops up of Amazon I worked on
the distributed storage replicated
storage for queing it's still I think
it's used by simple Q service at at its
back end and so I was in the middle of a
lot of conversations about design
choices when you build these large scale
systems using cues and event driven
architectures it quickly became apparent
that it's not the right obstruction
events and cues not the right
obstruction to build such systems so I
think there is one very important point
there is they are very good runtime
obstruction right so event driven
systems and cues give you awesome
runtime characteristics because for
example your service can have be slow
but other services are not slowed down
by that because things can be buffered
in cues or your service can be even down
and the other services don't even notice
that they just see messages may be not
coming or buffer it so runtime
characteristic of these systems is
awesome but as a design choice they
actually create very brittle systems
because everything is connected to
everything and there are Nu clear apis
and it's very hard to create the state
machine in every service and support all
the business logic so our team
recognized that and we started to think
about an orchestrator and Amazon had an
internal orchestrator based on Petr
Net's idea based on top of Oracle and it
was used to actually orchestrate orders
and we started to think about more
scalable Solutions we had three
different iterations three version of
the service internally and only third
version was public and it was released
as a simple workflow service simple
workflow service so it took us a lot of
kind of try different attempts to get it
right but I think even simple workflow I
don't think is fully I wouldn't say
we've got it right because it's still
not very popular service but we actually
learned a lot doing that and then what
happened is that we kind of left to
other companies and co-founder of
temporal Samaras who worked with me on a
simple workflow he went to Microsoft and
at Microsoft he wrote durable task
framework which later was adopted by
Azure functions and now Microsoft has
Azure durable functions and then we met
at Uber and we started to kind of we
created the simula we like took all
these ideas and created the Next
Generation of the technology which we
are kind of right now you can think of
this temporal temporal being the kind of
continuation all this previous attempts
over 10 years of iterations so can you
tell us the process of choosing to Fort
Cadence and create temporal as opposed
to say start over again how did you make
that decision the reason you would start
again if you believe that existing
solution is not good enough right the
new cence was solid because we ran it in
production for over fre years at tuber
at large scale and there over 100 use
cases using that for Mission critical
applications but we also knew that it
had a lot of um kind of there were a lot
of things we wanted to fix because over
three years we can of learn a lot but we
had a promise of full back compatibility
and live upgrades so we couldn't break
anything so getting from this point A to
point B without breaking it would be
extremely extremely hard it's possible
but it would be hard and when we for the
project we practically had all all
single time opportunity to fix a lot of
these little issues and just basic one
for example moving from fift to Proto
Buffs and from Custom Uber specific
protocol to JPC that the main things
which gives us a lot of benefits from
security point of view and so on and so
on and there are a lot of other little
things which we had to fix and we spent
a year since we fored the project until
we released the project and say it's
ready for production it took us a year
just working on the fork before we
released it because we put so many
changes there you mentioned MIT license
what parts of temporal are there to be
licensed I guess there's the client sdks
and there's the server or the web
interface like what are the different
parts of temporal so temporal is a has
backend cluster which has multiple roles
obviously you can run all these roles in
a single binary you have single binary
version for example you used for local
development which also includes UI but
you also can have all these five roles
and run them as separate pools of
workers pools of processes and backend
service also needs a database so we in
the open source we support MySQL
postgress and Cassandra and SQL light
also as officially supported databases
so this cluster connects to the database
exposes anpc interface for its front end
Ro and the whole cluster is MIT licensed
you can run it yourself and then when
you write your applications applications
external to the cluster so they contain
all the code and all business logic and
this application just connect to the
backend cluster for the JPC connection
and they applications don't need to open
any ports they only do outgoing
connection to the cluster so yeah all
these components MIT license I think
Java is Apache to licensed for
historical reasons because we initially
forked the implementation of the Amazon
framework which I built the simple
workflow we're going to go into core
temporal Concepts including workflows
activities timers and other things but
first I just want to mention some
previous episodes that are related to
either workflow systems or task systems
episode 502 Omar cats on distributed
task cues using celery episode 351
burned Rucker on orchestrating
microservices with workflow management
and episode 198 wheel Vander Al on
workflow management systems that last
episode is 10 years old but I was
surprised at a lot of the concepts are
still being discussed and still relevant
today so going into the these Core
Concepts you don't necessarily refer to
temporal as a workflow system but
workflow is one of the Core Concepts so
what can you tell me about workflows in
the context of temporal I think it's
very important to understand that when I
say workflow in context of temporal I
always me durable execution and durable
execution exactly concept I described
then you write quote in top level
programming language you can write code
in Java go typescript PHP python net and
this code is durable so we preserve the
full state including as I said block and
calls and all variables State all the
time and this is very highly applicable
to all sort of scenarios right every
time you need durability every time you
need guarantee of completion every time
you need to Saga brand compensations
temporal is very good fit there the
problem is that when you say usually say
workflow workflow engine people imagine
exactly the solutions you mentioned
which are just all yaml XML Jon based
and all like they draw pictures and
there is a reason these Solutions never
became popular like really popular
because most people will not Engineers
will not even consider them for the
majority of their use cases because
these systems now were designed kind of
to be developer friendly right like to
be developer first there is always this
promise that non-technical people will
write workflows because they can do
pictures reality is it never works right
Engineers still have to do this XML
andjon files or draw pictures and this
is not what Engineers want they want
code that's why when I say workflow
always mean durable execution and I
think it should be very very clear right
and which is very different from when
anyone else sells workflow they always
mean like gone file XML file or
something like that my experience with
say AWS step functions in Google Cloud
workflows where you do specify the
workflow as Json or yaml is that Json or
yaml are maybe really good for
configuration but what happens in those
systems is you're essentially writing
imperative code in the restricted
language and that to me is where things
start to get a lot less comfortable to
do that so tell me some of the technical
challenges is in implementing temporal
that does support arbitrary programming
languages or at least a good handful of
programming languages I realize that
each language has a different SDK to
support it but there must be some common
technology that's enabling this to
happen yeah so if you think about it
like there are only two approaches
really to preserve state of cod all the
time one approach would be that you can
after every practically cot progression
you snapshot memory of that code and you
store it somewhere and then if you need
to activate that execution on a
different machine you would load that
memory and you will continue executing
the problem is that you could probably
do it with some run times for example
you can do it with web assembly but you
cannot just take Java for example in
serialize full state of java execution
especially when it's blocked on some
threets if it's synchronous code at run
time or the same do the same thing with
go code right you cannot just take go
blocked on some code technically you
could but you need to hack runtime
pretty deeply the same thing for
typescript and so on so the other
approach would be to practically use
what we call replay you run the code
from the beginning and then every time
code executes some external action you
intercept that and then if this action
was already completed you just give
result to that code so if you let's say
as I said your code blocked on function
B and this process crashes you will have
a history of what we call event history
of the workflow when it will be
recording that action a was requested
and it was completed and action B was
requested but not completed yet and when
you will restart that practically that
process recover you will run this
function you will call a verify that
call to the a is in the history then you
will give result of a to the code and
code will go from line a to line B then
we'll validate that call B was done
right in it is in the history and then
we know that this code is blocked on B
right now and then we need to wait for B
result to deliver to the B there are a
lot of details there for example how do
you make sure that result of B is routed
to the process which is currently
waiting for it because the previous
process already crashed so there is the
whole routing layer there and there are
a lot of kind of other things and one
big assumption is that code of the
function is deterministic what it does
it mean it means that the code if you
execute it again will reach the same
point so for example if your code says
if random more than 50 take Branch a and
run for example call make API call a and
if it's less than 5050 make API call B
this code is not deterministic because
every time you run it from the beginning
it can take a different branch so if you
need to use random you proba need to use
deterministic random which will be
random first time you call it and then
it will return the same value you replay
and temporal provides special apis for
all these situations for random for time
for creating threads because threets
obviously are also not deterministic
unless you use our own runtime how about
a simple example I have my email or
messenger and I have a function where I
can send a message delayed by any amount
of time I specify and so this workflow
it's launched after some endpoint and
the user has communicated how long the
delay should be when I'm looking at the
workflow code it looks linear it looks
like starts out there's a sleep say a
timer and then we actually post the
message what happens the first time
through it hits that timer does it exit
or what exactly happens it's going to
allow it to be continued later so what
will happen is that uh wflow code runs
on the application space right it's not
it doesn't run within temporal cluster
and usually what you will do you will
create so we call Walker processes
workflow worker process which host
workflow code and this worker process
you can think it as a q consumer it's
the same like for you consume message
from Kafka you will have always running
process which cue consumer the same way
temporal worker it's always running it's
always listens on a specific que inside
of temporal called task q and it will
say I'm listening for task Q F right for
example for my workflow F register with
that task que so every when you start
workflow it will create a task in dat
the state inside of temporal itself and
then put task in that queue and it's all
transactional so we don't have rise
condition there and then this worker
will pick up this task it will contain
arguments of the workflow like
information about it and we start
executing that then it will hit this
sleep and it cannot make more progress
and this slep will be converted to the
create timer command and this command
will be sent back to the temporal server
and temporal will create durable timer
inside of its kind of infrastructure and
store this timer in the database and
then if you has sleep for example two
weeks two weeks later this timer will
fire it will create new task and new
worker kind of some probably different
process will pick up that task recover
workflow State unblock the timer and
continue so the worker doesn't exit but
the task has finished when that sleep
starts potentially exactly so there is
one more just optimization there is that
we will catch that workflow state for
some time inside of the Walker because
if sleep is short or just waiting for an
activity completion there is very high
probability that this workflow will be
needed again very soon so we don't want
to kind of recover it every time so we
will go and practically cat that
workflow for some time in the worker so
fast running workf flows are always
cashed so we only deliver new events to
them we don't need to do recovery but
this is purely optimization so talking
about ations what in your view or in
temporals view is sort of a short
duration workflow and what's long I know
in my experience often I'm having
conversations about workflows and I'm
thinking of just a very different scope
or very different duration than the
other person so I'm just curious from
temporals point of view or from your
experience with temporal users what's
the range of duration so first temporal
durable execution and is doesn't care
about duration so it can be used for in
situations when it's very very short and
and can be used in situation when it's
very very long it's all about durability
do you need guarantee of completion and
especially compensations for example
there are use cases when people use it
for instant payments so you have very
very small practically time balance
right like to actually execute that
operation but why do you need something
like temporal because if your some API
call fails you need to run compensations
right for example you took money from
one account you're trying to put it in
another account and another account
fails for some reason you return error
to the user very very fast but you need
to make sure that you will return money
to the original account and you need to
guarantee that so as we don't have
transactions across Services these days
temporal is the best way practically to
do this replacement for transactions in
the distributed architecture and this is
very common use case and it works even
if you have very short duration and you
have people waiting at the same time we
have use cases when workflows are always
running for example if you have workflow
we call them entity workflows so for
example you have a workflow which
represents a user and that workflow will
just handle all the communication to the
user I can give you one practical
example imagine you're Airline and you
want to have loyalty program so you have
points so you can absolutely have
workflow per customer running all the
time listening to events like for
example flight completed events and
every time you complete the flight it
gets the length of the flight and
increased number of points based on that
and points can be stored just as vflow
variables because they're always durable
and then if you reach certain number of
points you can run some actions like
activities to notify for example other
services that now you're a golden member
and if you want to have a timer inside
of workflow and once a month send email
saying okay this is your new number of
points by the way do you want this
promotion you can also Implement all of
that as a single prac workflow but the
point is this workflow is always running
there is no even end until customer
practically uh want to quit your system
which is practically never happens for
these type of scenarios I did run across
that idea of workflow as entities and I
do want to get into that a little bit
but let's go back to just the Core
Concepts we talked about workflows let's
do activities next so I mentioned before
in my delayed email case I was going to
use a sleep or a timer but an activity
is a more General concept can you tell
me what makes an activity in temporal
what are the properties that it should
have or needs to have so as I described
the approach temporal takes to recover
workflow state it does it fre replay so
practically the main requirement is that
quote is deterministic any external o is
not deterministic by definition because
it can succeed one time it can fail
other time it can return different
result so that's why temporal to
intercept those external calls
practically places a rule all external
communication goes through activities
and activities are just in every
language just a function so it's like
task right so can the same for example
you have q consumer can have task which
process that queue the same way in
temporal you write an activity which is
usually just a function and then this
function is invoked every time you
invoke this activity from the workflow
the code of this function we don't put
any limitation what can be in that
function nice thing about temporal
activities comparing for example to Q's
Q tasks is first temporal activities can
run as long as necessary you can run
them for a year if necessary obviously
for long run activities you want a
heartbeat you don't want activity which
will have one year time out and wait one
year until times out but it can hardbeat
every minute and as soon as your process
crashes it will be retried after 1
minute for example also you can add
information to the heartbeat so you can
store some information about your
progress in the heartbeat so for example
if your activity is scanning a huge data
set it can just heartbeat progress on
every record and then if activity fails
it will restarted you can say get last
hard bit data get your progress and
continue from that set so you can have
activities which are that and also
activities are cancelable so if activity
heartbeats it can be cancelled so it can
hand gracefully handle cancellation and
also we can route activity to specific
host so for example if you need to run
activity on host B of your Fleet for
because activity a downloaded some file
there you can route activity to that
host specifically so we have a lot of
kind of features and also activity if
they fail they retry exponentially we
have exponential retry and retry can be
as long as you want so if you want to
retry for a week you want to retry for a
months it's absolutely supported it's
very different from cues because
duration of activities and number of
retries is usually very very limited so
activities could definitely be on a
remote system some kind of remote
procedure call or web interface but are
there cases where even though it's in
the same process you'd want to consider
it an activity so practically it's a
temporal kind of limitation I wouldn't
say limitation it's just this designed
choice that every external iio should
live in an activity so we have a concept
of a local activity which runs in the
same process as a workflow as an
optimization in certain scenarios it
allows to do very very low latency
scenarios they might require that but
again if you for example your activity
sends an email this should be an
activity and then what workflow will
call send email activity I think we
talked about the need for determinism
there's another concept that always
comes up with distributed systems is
item potency I'm guessing that all your
activities need to be item potent or are
they only going ever be called once that
is a very good point so temporal doesn't
retry activities blindly if activity
fails or times out there is an
Associated retri policy if you specify
Max attempt in this policy maximum
number number of attempts to one it will
not be retried it also but what will
happen in this case in this case
workflow will get an error and we'll
need to handle that right and it's you
just use usual language obstructions for
example if it's Java you would say try
catch catch this exception activity
failed and then you can handle it anyway
for examp you can run compensations
different activities so it's a little
bit more sophisticated than just oh we
would blindly retry but in reality the
most common approach to deal with these
type of scenarios is make activities
important and just do blind retries by
default we retry them but I think
important point is temporal is fully
consistent system so it doesn't do blind
retries only if you ask them but if you
specify Max attempt to one there is
possibility that your activity will
never run right because maybe it's
delivered task is delivered timer is
started and then process crashed so in
this case temporal guarantees that after
timeout the exception will be erased and
it will be delivered to the workflow so
it cannot lose that activity but it can
get to the situation when it's never
executed if you have Max attempt of one
and then you will need to handle error
yourself so yes but if you do it
important then you don't think about it
right you just say Okay retry Forever
Until it's uh done so you mentioned Saga
pattern a while ago is that something
that temporal helps you implement I
guess first of all what is the Saga
pattern I think it relates to this idea
of I have multiple activities maybe I've
successfully performed some of them but
one of them fails and I want to undo the
other other ones or can you just kind of
tell us how that works I'm not sure how
it's exactly formulated but let me
describe how I see it the idea is
exactly that that if you execute
multiple API calls and these API calls
probably perform some storage changes
and perform some changes and as you
don't have transactions across those
calls if for example most obvious one
money transfer take money from one
account put money in another account you
took money from first account and then
you cannot put money on second account
because maybe your account ID is wrong
so what do you do in this case as
there's no transaction the only thing
you can technically do is run a
compensation action and compensation
action would be put money back on the
account a right and this scenario
appears all the time so you practicly
need to run compensations and Saga is
just a kind of pattern which says yes if
you run multiple activities so you run
like 10 of them and eight of them
succeeded but nine failed how do I go
and run compensations for previous eight
and I think important point about
temporal comparing to any other
framework especially all this existing
framework based on Json and yaml that
because code is very Dynamic it makes
implementing sagas very trivial because
think about what is Saga Saga is
guarantee of compensation temporal
guarantees that your function will keep
running even if processes crash or other
outages happen so temporal can easily
guarantee that this process will come
keep running if something happened and
if your process has TR cage block and if
you got exception and cage block you run
compensations it's very easy guarantee
for temporal and then you can write
special classes for examp temporal has
like Saga class in Java when all this is
just collection of callbacks right and
then when you say compensate we just go
and execute this callbacks and each of
the callbacks can contain some
compensation logic important part is
because it's Dynamic imagine you have
like 50 possible activities and you have
complex Branch branching logic that
every time you execute some transaction
you execute like I don't know five of
these activities but every time which
five activities you execute is different
this temporal you Willa just pass the
Saga down every practically Branch you
will accommodate which activities were
executed in the list and then when you
compensate you will compensate those
five activities try doing that any
static deck kind of graph generated
through yam XML because you don't have
Dynamic compensations you practically
need to go and model every path and
compensation path separately it
pratically becomes unmanageable after a
few possible branches we found that this
is very common misunderstanding how
sagas should be implemented and
something which is Trivial in temporal
practically impossible to do in any kind
of other configuration based language so
in that case it sounds like the per
language SDK is providing a pretty
sophisticated little piece of technology
to help you with this Saga whereas in a
workflow system based on a configuration
language that just isn't that element
unless the system were to provide it
interesting thing that Saga is not
sophisticated because sophisticated part
of the SDK is providing that your code
will keep running right and the full
state is preserved Saga itself as I said
is a class which you can write in 20
minutes because all it is is just list
of compensations and then you say
compensate you just go over a list and
run these callbacks I wrote this Saga
class in like less than one hour so
anyone can write their own and they can
write their this is thing it's code you
can write your own libraries you can
write your own Frameworks and temporal
as runtime guarantees completion of code
and guarantees varability so one way to
call this is Fault oblivious right your
code doesn't even need to know that some
fault happened because it recovered
seamlessly that brings to mind the term
like separation of concerns so the
workflow code as I'm looking at it is
focused on on this happy path of things
working and I don't necessarily have to
worry about the retries that's kind of
the goal I think are two type failures
there are failures which are
infrastructure failures and process
crashes Network going down right like
power outages like things which are not
relate to your business logic andoral
takes care of all of them seamlessly you
don't need to even think about that
they're not part of your code and you
don't need to persist state to survive
in recovery because state is always
persisted every local variable in your
code is durable but then there are
business level failures for examp as I
said for example if you say deposit to
account and account ID is wrong not much
you can do on the info level right this
is your business logic and then you can
practically throw an exception and you
can deal with that exception and in
activity you can differentiate which
exceptions are retriable and which
exceptions are non- retriable you proba
say Okay run account ID is non-
retriable exception then it will be
propagated to the workflow and then
workflow will run Saga compensation to
return money but if it's like activity
failed because of timeout or database or
some other random thing on all poter it
will be retried so that is kind of the
idea other interesting thing is that
intermittent problems can become
problems which you fix in two hours for
example you get now pointer you look at
the Cod oh yeah I have a bu for example
this is different Cod puff activity
keeps ret trying you just go deploy new
cod with the bu fix and 2 hours later it
can on the next ret TR it goes through
you don't need to do anything your workf
flows just keep running as nothing
happened because every deployment never
will interrupt them that is very
powerful Paradigm that can fix things in
production while they are going without
losing when people come to temporal
first approach is oh let me fail
workflow in any intermittent error they
like no you don't need to do that you
can keep retrying as long as you want
right so you don't need to even think
about this like try to introduce manual
processes which people right now deal
with manual process they have dead
letter qes which should be manually done
these all sort of processes scripts and
all of that goes away it takes some time
to internalize it's not something people
are used to that you don't even need to
think about this type of problems but I
think it's super powerful after you kind
of learn temporal deeply so you're
talking about a developer who's Maybe
working with operations or is dealing
with operations and the identify a
problem that's going to involve probably
the web interface of temporal can you
tell me a little bit about what
information that provides and what's the
usefulness of it uh nice thing about
temporal because as I said we record
every event in the workflow so we use
practically event sourcing to recover
state of the workflow it means that we
record everything so every activity in
vacation you see arguments every
activity completion you see result if
activity fails and your workflow stock
you can see why activities failing how
many retries where when the next retry
so you can see all the information you
can see all steps which executed so far
with all the arguments and everything so
and all timing like every timer and so
on so you can easily understand what's
going on so you have deep visibility in
worst case scenario let's say you're
getting null pointer and you don't
understand why you're getting that
because it's a very complex code PA you
can press a button download the workflow
history in Json format plug into your
debugger practically in your code in
your debugger and Replay that workflow
as many times as you want reproducing
that problem on your local machine so
it's super powerful like triple shooting
technique so UI gives you all sort of
visibility into single workflow
including history and different views
also we allow you listing because you
can have hundreds of millions of
workflows billions workflows running in
your system so we have prct index and
your custom attributes and you can list
workflows filter workflows based on
different criteria also count them based
on that criteria so you can find okay
give me all workflows from this customer
which failed yesterday and you can list
them and you can go investigate deeper
each of these workflows also temporal is
integrated with usual metrics context
propagation login so you get all the
normal Integrations which you ACC
company has these metrics for example so
to kind of be alarmed for example if
something goes wrong because we meet
metrics automatically on every activity
every workflow every retry so everything
which is important is emitted so you
don't need to actually add any custom
metrics to start making sense out of
your application I think we've covered
all the core concept workflows
activities timers how it runs the event
history replay retries on errors and the
web interface for debugging let's go
back to something you mentioned earlier
this idea of workflows as entities and I
think in that case these are workflows
that never finish or never terminate
unless the entity goes away I guess and
I think you alluded to two things there
signals and queries can you talk about
signals and queries because those didn't
immediately seem like workflow concept
that I was familiar with so we now have
signal queries and updates update was
recently added so a signal is one way
call into the workflow so practically
it's a delivering an event to the
workflow to specific workflow instance
so you say signal workflow you give
workflow ID by the way workflow ID is uh
provided by the application developer
and we guarantee uniqueness by workflows
by ID so there is hard guarantee that
you know will have two workflows with
the same ID running at the same time in
the system so you get practically
exactly once execution guarantees for
workflows so signal is just a vent and
how it's handled it depends on the
language for example in Java it will be
just a call back you say for this signal
type this is my arguments and every time
this event is sent to the workflow the
call back will be called and workflow
can react to that and it can be fully
asynchronous kind of piece of code a
query is the way to get information out
of the workflow synchronously So when
you say query you call back inside of
the workflow this call back cannot
mutate workflow state it only can return
data but it can return any data out of
your workflow it's your code so you can
return picture you can return just
status you can return whatever and color
blocks synchronously so if you want to
show something in UI about this workflow
you will say query it will block as soon
as data is returned it will show
something in the UI and the update is
kind of both together so update is you
send the request to the workflow and
this is a call back into the workflow
workflow will block this call back as
long as necessary and then it will
return result at some point and your
caller will be unblocked and there are
two ways to invoke update for them can
be synchronous for short lift requests
for example instant payments and things
like that but it also will have a
synchronous update when it can be
actually taken much longer time and it
will do some optimized long polling for
the result on the background but
conceptually we have signal which is one
way event query which is just get
information out of the workflow an
update which is practically say imagine
you have this entity workflow and you
want to say I want to I don't know take
some promo and do something so it will
be update VF will updates it State maybe
run some activities and then unblock
your update call giving you information
about success like or rejection of this
promo actually give me one more example
with update I'm not totally clear on
that just walk me through it again okay
let me give you a different example
imagine you want to implement page flow
like wizard right show page one like I
don't know you are implementing a
checkout pipeline right I I worked at
Amazon at the ordering service so I kind
of have some ideas there so you have
checkout pipeline so you show something
first page for example your shopping
cart right then you select a few buttons
that you say next right based what you
selected next page will be different
then you do whatever payments
information you say next next page is
different this update you could have
let's say check out pipeline workflow
and then you say here's my and you'll be
blocked waiting practically for that
page to return data and then you will
say okay here's my data this will
unblock boxl can execute any logic
including running activities and then it
can say okay now show different page
right and it will return practically New
Page information and also will get
blocked there so you can model the whole
wizard is this practically blocking
workflow imagine right show page one
blah blah blah business logic show page
two blah blah blah business logic and it
can be as complex as you want because
it's code and it practically State full
session as a workflow dat is a very good
way to implement that how about
interceptors that's something that maybe
is strictly on the client side I wasn't
sure so at this point we only have
client side interceptors we are
considering server side because there
are some scenarios for them but the idea
of Interceptor is that sometimes you
want to create functionality which is
kind of AAL to the specific business use
case for example I don't know can be as
simple as I want to save every time some
activity completes I want to save it in
some emit event right an event to Kafka
to go to my warehouse you can write an
Interceptor because we intercept all the
API calls to workflow and from the
workflow and you can say Interceptor
which will run an activity which
publishes to Kafka for example after
every activity completion and then you
just register this Interceptor with the
Walker and every workflow will
automatically get that function and are
obviously a lot of use cases for
interceptors they allow not to wrap apis
because before interceptors existed
people would say oh now I need to wrap
temporal apis to get this functionality
but now you can write an Interceptor and
your normal workflows using standard
apis will get these benefits out of the
box so you have some cross cutting
concern that you want to kind of inject
into every workflow you're writing
exactly or activity I think that'll let
us segue into talking about the client
sdks the per language sdks so I think we
covered the Core Concepts and we covered
some more additional Concepts so you
have sdks for go Java PHP Python
typescript and coming soon
isnet I read though that at least some
of the client libraries are built on a
rust core can you talk about how that
came about and yet there's no rust SDK
so can you kind of just tell us what the
structure of the client sdks is so our
clients are pretty fat clients because
they Implement a pretty complex State
machine because you need to make sure
that this code execution re execution is
correct and the API of the server just
gives you a history so proba get a bunch
of events and you to convert that pra
through a lot of State machine to actual
code execution we also want to make
every SDK as native to the language user
as possible right so if you are using
typescript you want to feel like you run
normal typescript you don't do anything
unnatural right if you're using another
net you want to use normal a I sync from
net right if you are doing pyone for
example we use iyn iio from pyone and if
you do jav we actually do blocking calls
you just do synchronous calls because
Java doesn't have really something like
a we I thinkc yet right and then every
like if you do go you want to do
channels and select and so on so it
means that every DEC is pretty first
contains this logic how to make it as
language Native as possible but then
underneath there is very complex State
machine and we found is that this common
state machine is probably 80% of the the
code and the complexity and what we did
we decided to write a single Library
which will kind of encapsulate all this
complexity and we'll kind of thought
about what we would write it in and we
found that rust would be actually very
good fit first because rust integrates a
with a lot of Li languages pretty well
so there are very good native
Integrations with python for example
with like a lot of languag also allows
you to do cpis as well if you need and
so and also we just our development team
just like Ras for obvious reasons like
it's let's say this way after we wrot it
project took a year it's a very complex
project I don't think we ever had any
like crashes right or anything which is
beyond logical bug we had logical bugs
in it obviously but we never had like
bugs related to the implementation which
is amazing for this such a complex piece
of technology so the rust core is just
library and then pyone net typescript
they all sit on top of that library and
then just much much simpler
implementations our Java and go which
were written before the core they still
implement this state machines
independently there are some benefits to
that because mostly for example I know
that go Java developers don't like
libraries for examp python developers
are okay having shared Library linked to
their code but Java developers don't
like that so we are not sure if we going
to ever like put core there we are
thinking about different ways to do that
but conceptually it would be ideal if
you put put every SDK on the core but
we'll see and we one day we absolutely
we just wasn't a priority we absolutely
will have rust core rust SDK on top of
this core SDK we didn't have enough time
and resources to prioritize that one
workflow feature that I imagine is
required in all of these languages would
be parallel execution so I have five
tasks I want to run all at the same time
I don't necessarily know which one is
going to take the longest can you
describe that process in whichever
language you like to use it as an
example how do we do parallel execution
uh yeah it depends very heavily depends
on the language let's say Java you would
just invoke them asynchronously get a
back promise promise very similar to
future but it's temporal specific for
practical reasons of determinism and
then you will just say Loop over those
promises and say promise. get and block
there until or you can just say wait for
first promise to be ready from this list
if you want a more complex logic and if
you're using something like I don't net
you will just use quing functions right
and then you will wait on those tasks
which we returned from those calls so
you just use normal language constructs
to do parallel execution there is
nothing magical about that so in go you
could use gortin so you could run just
five parallel gortin other option is in
go you can invoke activities and it will
return future so you can just use a sync
type of programming using future get so
you have options but you have full power
of go language including go routines to
implement parallel processing so echoing
back to how temporal works and how
replaying event works but tying it to
this parallel execution case suppose I
do launch Five tasks in parallel and
let's say they're all long running I'm
curious what happens when one of them
finishes now let's say my code is going
to wait on all of them to finish does my
workflow keep getting rerun sort of as
each one finishes or does the system
know to wait for all of them right now
we don't have server site weight for all
of them workflow will be notified about
each of them completed and then it will
continue blocking so they are not very
long running bflow will be cashed so it
won't be very expensive but still there
is some overhead there if they are very
long running yes vflow will be recovered
multiple times but again if they're so
long running probably it's not a problem
we consider it some feature more like
okay N5 workflow only when all of them
are already but so far just it's an
optimization I don't think it was really
paino for everyone so far so let's
finish up with talking about the client
sdks then we're going to move on to
temporal cluster and temporal Cloud
let's start with the cluster can you
talk about what is involved in setting
that up as a developer I know there's a
single binary how that works and then
how would you move on to a production
implementation yeah so for local
development and if you're on Mac you
just do bro install temporal you get
temporal binary temporal CLI plus full
featur it server in a single binary and
then just say temporal start Dev server
and by default it can start server with
in memory sqlite database so it's pretty
good for development because every time
you restart that you just remove all the
state which is nice so and you also get
the UI so you just have a UI ring on
Local Host so you can web UI so as soon
as you have the single binary you have
full environment to to do development I
think one thing I forgot to mention we
also have unit testing Frameworks which
don't require server so it means that
for example if in Java you want to unit
test your workflow you just use our
supporting classes and they will work
even if your workflow blocks for a long
time for example if uh workflow says
sleep two weeks and unit testing
Frameworks will discover that and jump
time two weeks ahead the moment workflow
is blocked so you can test in
milliseconds workflows which run for
weeks it's unit testing but then if you
want to do real development then you do
single binary but then you can deploy to
your infrastructure and then it depends
how you also can locally some people use
Docker compost if you want to have mooic
installations you absolutely can use
Docker compost which runs temporal roles
as separate Docker containers and you
can for example if you want to look how
metrics look then you would use Docker
compost because single binary doesn't
include Prometheus for example then how
people deploy temporal itself is just
binary compil from go backend server
written in go so you can deploy it any
way you want so if you want to run it on
bare metal you absolutely can deploy
temporal binaries SCP those binaries to
50 machines and configure them correctly
make sure that this machines can talk to
each other because temporal requires
direct communication and after that it
just will work and then you probably
want to make sure you put load balancer
in front of your front ends but
obviously these days most people don't
do that they use kubernetes or use some
other similar technology and then you
just deploy temporal through Helm chart
there is Helm chart and or you write
your own Helm chart to to deploy that or
you use whatever ECS and so on so
temporals absolutely not opiate how you
run those binaries right there are
certain requirements around frontend
load balancer and communication between
nodes and then you need database you
need to provision database you need to
provision schema and then you just give
connection temporal cluster to the
database speaking of database you
mentioned the inmemory I think it was my
SQL for the single binary sqlite oh
sorry sqlite and then you mentioned
restarting it is in a way a good thing
because it resets the state so what
exactly is in the database is it
strictly workflows that are currently
executing with maybe some history for
debugging or what else is contained in
there so it contains workflow State
history of the workflow and index of
workflows if you need to list workflows
across like list multiple workflows and
uh there are technical things for
example durable timers that because
workflow state by itself is not enough
right for example if it's sleeping for
30 days you want to have a durable timer
and and we have a lot of kind of other
moving Parts but conceptually from your
point of view yes workflow State history
tasks and uh index in production
deployment we recommend especially if
you have large scale we integrate with
elastic search for that so index would
be in the elastic search going back to
the workflows as entities if in that
case some of my workflows will run
potentially forever is there a decision
to be made about how much State I allow
to be in the workflow versus still
having separate database of my own is
that a decision to be made and what do
you feel people tend to do with that
it's a very good question so for example
the use case I described for airline
points I know very large scale
production use cases which don't use
database they just store State there at
the same time it's not that much state
right it just points and maybe IDs to
the dup of events uh like some recent
events to the dup so but just some basic
limitations we don't store state of the
workflow directly we only store state of
the results of activities because we
record events so workflow input
arguments and activity State results
would be the state so if you activ and
we limit the size of the history to 50
megabytes so if you have every activity
result cannot be larger than 2 megabytes
so technically even 25 activities
returning 2 megabytes will exceed that
limit so we recommend that so if you
need to pass large blobs temporal is not
the technology to pass large blobs
around we recommend storing blobs in
some other system and passing poters
around so we're not Big Data System One
caveat with always run in workflows with
entity workflows is Imagine they run
forever let's say they have some event
Loop processing events and size of this
history becomes unbounded right because
it will keep growing so we have special
mechanism we call it Contin is new when
you can practically kind of do this tail
recursion elimination when you kind of
call this workflow again from the
beginning and you pass States explicitly
and then history is reset to the new to
zero so practicly this workflows are
expected periodically call this
operation to reset set the history size
so this way they can run forever and
have unlimited practical duration and
length that is kind of the mechanism we
provide also it allows to upgrade code
because upgrading code is nontrivial
when theflow already started so if you
call this continues new periodically
there is guarantee around code upgrade
so it makes it also easier I think
you're alluding to workflow versioning
which is something I was going to touch
on but now might be a good time that
does seem like a challenge so especially
if you have these workflows that are
running a long time the code can
potentially change how do you know if
workflow execution is compatible with
the new code or vice versa yeah that is
in general a hard problem imagine
updating code while something is in
Flight right so there are two approaches
to versioning in all kind of workflow
like long running systems one is you
just pin the version the moment you
start the workflow you pratically say
this workflow started with version one
and then you deploy version two and you
say this workflow is pined to version
two and then uh you cannot really fix
the back in version one right because
all new workflows will benefit from the
changes it works very well for
relatively short workflows if your
workflows up to 1 hour like a day it's
actually very common approach and we
recommend that because it just makes
your life easier but if you have
workflow which runs for a months and it
doesn't call contain is new because it's
just sequence of steps which takes a
month then being able to deploy and run
pool of walkers for every version
becomes down in task and it can be just
not practical so temporal provides a way
to still provide what we call it
patching being able to patch workflows
which are already running and we do it
by just practically keeping two versions
of the code you have old version of the
code and new version of the code inside
of your code and you can put it any
place you can be Library it can be just
one function you can do it multiple
places but you just say if old version
keep old code new version new code and
then when you have API call you can
verify that all workflows on the old
version completed then you can remove
old branches but it allows you
practically to fix bugs in workflows
which already running and guarantee that
they're compatible because we have
special practically conditions in
versioning and then we provide ways to
test that so we have unit testing
support and replay support to ensure
that you didn't broke compatibility by
mistake versioning does sound like it
can get complicated but I imagine if you
didn't even have an explicit
representation of your workflow at all
then versioning is still going to be a
huge problem if you just weren't using a
workflow system like this it's much
worse it's impossible because you can do
trivial changes back is compatible
change but the moment you need to do in
aable change because your logic is
spread out across multiple Services your
sequen in logic is just everywhere and
it's not in one place it's practically
impossible I can tell you we had
customers we said they're stuck they
cannot do changes they're scared because
they don't know what's going to break
because like event driven systems
especially like choreography based
systems you can think them as like one
big Global set of global variables
because when people say oh it's good
that you can publish message and some
service will consume it without ever me
knowing it's not a good idea it's like
Global variable you update it you have
no clue which other parts of your code
will be broken so this systems extremely
hard to maintain and guarantee that
they're not going to break with changes
so these next topics about temporal
cluster I think are going to lead us
into talking about temporal Cloud
because we're going to talk about when
you need to scale up what happens and
how do you manage that so there's an
idea of multicluster
replication is that for performance or
for reliability or both it's purely for
reliability let me talk about
performance first and scalability and
then we talk about multicluster temporal
as it's designed is designed to scale uh
almost infinitely practically it can
saturate any database so far we couldn't
find database we couldn't saturate so it
means that if you have an application on
temporal and it's configured correctly
and your cluster is configured correctly
the bottleneck is always a database and
a CPU on database so what happens is
that MySQL and post grass there is no
Shing built in so you can only scale up
I know that some companies use vs uh so
it's possible to scale them out out we
don't provide direct support for that
but in most cases you kind of can get
the biggest I don't know Aurora instance
and you can scale up to certain point
but then you hit the wall if you use
Cassandra Cassandra allows you to scale
out adding more hosts and this Cassandra
you can go much larger scale so we seen
people running 100 not Cassandra
clusters to run certain workloads and
temporal can keep up like cluster itself
can always keep up this database so that
is how you would do that if your use
case is a low rate you can pick my SQL
of postgress fine but if you to go high
rates then you will need to probably
Cassandra if you're running a self-
served version of temporal and going
back to the multicluster so temporal has
very unique way to guarantee relability
across regions and across availability
like so every cluster can be deployed to
availability zones right you can
absolutely deploy Cassandra to be in
free availability zones you can deploy
temporo cluster to be distributed so it
can sustain single zone outage without
problem but what happens if the whole
region goes down or database gets
corrupted so temporal allows you to run
more cluster in different regions and
these clusters absolutely independent
they have their own storage even
different type of storage so one cluster
can run my SQL another cluster can run
Cassandra for example and they
communicate through top level like high
level application protocol which is
temporal specific we should practice
ship events right we ship the same
events we put into the event history and
what it means is that temporal this
cluster is so independent that there is
no bless radius problem you cannot give
a single command which would break for
example both clusters so architecture
it's much more available system with
anything you see out there especially
databases which are multi- region
databases because these databases you
can always give single schema update or
single B command which will bring down
the whole system as we know most of the
outages are operatory error upgrade
error version error andoral allows you
to run this clusters even on different
versions so by Design this multi- region
set up and fill overs are very very
highly available and it's also because
it's a synchronous replication for
because for performance we don't want to
do like wait for round trips to the
remote region they actually have
conflict resolution code because
databases they just look at the last
time stamp and drop data which is beyond
that temporal actually detects conflicts
and has conflict resolution code which
allows for them not losing data and
events even in case of conflicts for
example if there was not every event was
propagated before fail over things like
that so certainly our multi- region
support is very very powerful and a lot
of companies when it was written a tuber
that was main requirement to run like
important workloads you couldn't run
tier one workload without having this
surviving full data center outage multi
full region outage that doesn't mean
that it doesn't create performance right
this is purely for availability because
every cluster is independent it has its
own scale limits assumption is that
remote cluster can keep up with the same
scale so usually they have the same size
but each individual name space can be
fill over individually temporal has
notion of name spaces so it's
multitenant system so you don't need to
fill over the whole cluster you can fill
over individual name space if necessary
but it does make cluster faster it just
make it more reliable so I think that's
a good introduction to temporal Cloud
cuz you mentioned Nam spaces and I think
you're building the cloud as a nam space
as a service and not just a hosted
cluster can you tell me the difference
between those two concepts and what are
the advantages of namespace as a service
so open source has notion of namespace
so if you deploy a cluster you can
create multiple name spaces in that but
you still have a cluster in temporal
Cloud we just give you name space and
cluster concept is not even exposed
obviously behind the scenes we still
have clusters but it's our problem it's
not problem of the user of the cloud
it's the same as you go to S3 and you
say create new bucket you absolutely
unaware about the back end of S3 right
maybe they have clusters maybe they
don't right maybe it's one I doubt it's
one right but it's absolutely hidden the
same thing with temporal Cloud you get a
namespace you probably go through API
say create new namespace you get
namespace and point you can start using
it right away and temporal to provide
scalability and reliability of that name
space and we can scale up practically
infinitely on a single name space we ran
tests when we ran 300,000 actions per
second and we could go higher just we
didn't want to pay higher at the B bill
for that so we can go very high frut use
cases on that and the reason we can do
that because we practically wrote Our
Own storage as I said storage is
pluggable so we can have different
databases and we wrote Our Own database
and the reason we can do it because we
wrote database practic for a single API
call certainly we don't have resources
to write general purpose database and
maintain our system but what we did we
realized that temporal has very specific
access patterns and it's built for very
specific update and read patterns and we
wrote database just for that practic
single like very very narrow use case it
allows to be super super efficient and
super fast and scalable just for that
use case it's certainly not a general
purpose database but it allows our Cloud
scale well beyond for example anything
you can reach with Cassandra or and also
provide higher availability than any of
the existing databases out there you
mentioned as three and I imagine your
situation is similar where you need to
accommodate a large dynamic range of
customers exer sizes so you might have a
lot of customers starting out they're
just getting used to temporal and
they're really using a fraction of a
cluster on your side but then you have
customers that have hit their stride
maybe multiple teams are adopting
temporal they could scale up and
essentially be using multiple clusters
worth of compute behind the scenes we
are multitenant we actually don't
provide clusters as I said so every
cluster can run multiple customers name
spaces for multiple customers and we
certainly perform some logic to allocate
name spaces to clusters to make sure
that they evenly distributed also we
obviously give enough Headroom and we
also a some ofos scaling features to be
able to sustain spikes and we can have
customers which have very high frut and
low frut also as you said if you have
multiple teams using temporal every team
probably will have their own name spaces
so they are not even need to be in the
same cluster but at the same time if you
have Nam space and use case which
requires extremely high rate we
absolutely can support that an example
for example every Snapchat story update
is a temporal workflow going through our
Cloud so we can go very high rate an
imagine number of Snapchat stories at
New Year's Eve or Super Bowl so one of
the reasons SN is using our servic is
they don't need to think about scaling
up for these events because it's on
temporal service itself how about
retention with temporal cloud or
analytics I imagine that you don't want
the same database being used for the
real time workflows as I might want to
use to run analytics on the last year's
worth of jobs is there any combination
for that yeah so you can store workflows
in side of namespace up to 3 months into
Pro Cloud right now we might increase
that in the future but after that or
before it can any time you have option
to configure expert feature an expert is
practically just taking your workflow
history in appropriate format and just
putting that into your own s fre bucket
so practically all after workflow is
complete we give it to you and then you
can do whatever you want with them so
you want to run just keep them for
compliance forever or you want to run
some a redu job on them you absolutely
can do all of that so that is a very
common scenario for export and that kind
of relates to observability in general
since this is running in the cloud what
sort of hooks do I have if I want to do
my own I don't know debugging or
accounting or first you obviously you
get the UI one thing I forgot to mention
we also everything UI does is doing for
the well- defined JPC interface so you
absolutely can build your own version of
UI let's say doing that second is that
we have CLI so everything you do in UI
even more you can do for CLI which talks
to the same interface so absolutely can
look at the workflow list workflows like
send signals send commands and so on uh
queries through CLI so CLI is pretty
powerful in the cloud you also get
access to the same UI even more powerful
and then you have CLI and for metrics we
can expose specific and point to do
Prometheus metrix so you can configure
your own endpoint through like with your
own certificate so you would be able to
access your own metrics also sdks most
of the metrics actually mitted by sdks
so only some metrics which are server
side only and not visible by sdks I Meed
through that endpoint mostly performance
related which are needed to optimize
your workload which exposed by through
the cloud but you have access to that
and if I need to encrypt my inputs and
outputs and so I can't natively observe
them on the UI there's a codec server
something that's going to allow me to
see the actual data yeah okay let me
just give a big picture here first I
think the first thing when we say oh if
you don't want to for example you want
to use temporal Cloud versus open open
source version very common answer
immediately there is no way we would
ever use your SAS offering right like
this temporal Cloud it's your SAS
offering and it's a usual reaction what
happens is that after we go and explain
how temporal Cloud works most people say
oh yeah it's absolutely practical and we
can pass security review and we pass
security reviews of biggest banks in the
world so which are very very strict why
few things first as you mentioned
encryption so temporal is not a database
doesn't need to look into the data sent
to the backend cluster right first is
that code runs on your premises right
because temporal just keeps the backend
cluster the same way is confluent runs
your kasaa cluster and you run your
application which publishes and reads
from that cluster on your premises the
same way is temporal you link the SDK
you deploy application into your system
any way you want temporal doesn't know
how you deploy your application all it
needs to do is connection to the
temporal cluster you need only outgoing
connection from your VPC or your data
center to temporal because temporal
never connects back it's always your
code to temporal it's through JPC so you
need only one port to open there and
then you run your code it's only
outgoing connections and then you can
encrypt everything before sending there
because temporal never looks in the
payloads so if you have an activity
input of workflow input it will be
encrypted using your codec server your
encryption algorithm your keys and you
never temporal will never see anything
clear text and then we have a special UI
plugin practically in UI you can say
okay I'm running JavaScript in my
browser I want a cadc which is local to
my VPC and browser will directly connect
to that cadc server and decrypt things
if I have permissions so temporal Cloud
never sees that because UI runs in your
browser so everything un encrypted data
never leaves your kind of internal data
center or your VPC so I think this is
important to understand is that like
three things you don't tempor doesn't
run your code it never sees anything in
clear text and no connections besides
the connection to the temporal endpoint
and these three things are enough to
pass practice security view of the most
strict organizations and I think that
goes back to the start of the show
talking about separation of concerns
which is that temporal doesn't need to
know these inner details of my code
because that's just not its domain
that's not what it's responsible for
correct yeah because temporal doesn't
understand your workflow logic it
doesn't see any of your code all it sees
is practically events right run this
activity complete this activity and
create this timer run this timer so it's
very kind of lowlevel details but your
business logic lives in your code and
temporal never sees it okay that makes a
lot of sense how about pricing how does
that work with temporal Cloud so we are
100% consumption based so it means that
you pay only for what you use and unit
of consumption is what we call Action so
every activity execution is an action
every signal is an action and we charge
I think the highest price without any
discounts is like $25 for million
actions which means that for a lot of
use cases it's almost free only if you
run something hundred thousands times
per second then these things can add up
to larger numbers but then we have
discounts we have volume discounts up to
70% based on what you do this are also
allows us to actually close deals with
even large companies Because the actual
deal contains zero dollars right because
it's all about permission to run
workloads and then you just there is no
upfront cost you don't need to go and
invest in temporal I know whatever
amount of money to buy seats and so on
it's purely how much we are going to use
one interesting detail about our
organization our sales people are paid
only on consumption so they not paid if
you buy credits they're not paid if you
sign some deal they don't pay every time
you sign paperwork they only get paid
when there is actual consumption on our
cloud and it creates such a huge
alignment that we've got feedback from
our customers that the probably most
friendly sales organization they
encounter it all right I think that
covers temporal Cloud we have to start
wrapping up now you mentioned the single
binary is been a good way to get started
with temporal is there any other advice
you have for someone just start out
where do they look is it on the website
videos what do you recommend I
absolutely recommend doing our courses
so if you go to our website and I think
in resources we have links to how to
learn temporal and we have getting
started guides and we also have courses
absolutely recommend doing courses we
have one one one or two courses for all
major languages and if you want to just
learn temporal understand temporal
anyone who starts with that absolutely
recommend to do the course because it's
code but you need to understand how
these things works right there is too
much magic because the way I describe it
looks like magic but when you do the
course you understand how magic works it
becomes obvious and then you just can
focus on your application without kind
of thinking and running into some age
cases so absolutely please do the
courses also join our slack community so
we have Community Forum we have our
slack around 9,000 people in the slack I
think right now so we have pretty
healthy Community which people get help
there all the time so please and you can
find me there as well so if you go stra
now slack my name is there so Max fa you
can always find me there and ask
questions how about when users are
Advanced and they want to get involved
in implementations since it is open
source is there special channels on the
slack for that or is there mailing list
there is a channel on the slack and also
it's all in GitHub so you can always
file issues and requests and so on so
you can communicate with that as well
there are quite a few large
contributions especially around these
Decay for example Ruby's DEC was
contributed by coinbase and I think
right now stripe and coinbase maintain
that together so I think there is also
scull SDK there is uh there are some
other sdks being written so these are
the biggest contributors I think right
now also there are companies Building
open source project like people build
open source project using temporal as an
engine so that is also pretty common use
case oh can you explain that for a
little bit I wasn't clear so as an
engine how does that work so one example
I can give probably is Netflix for
example the internal version of Spiner
required practically cicd pipeline right
and deployment pipeline they rewrote
that using temporal as an underline
implementation so imagine you are trying
to do startup which creates new machine
learning whatever platform and it's open
source for example you absolutely can
build you take temporal as a core and
then build your business logic around
that so you can absolutely build much
more complex applications and save a lot
of time right because you probably just
write your business logic and we
actually have startup program I forgot
to mention that because a lot of
startups like us it's a very good value
proposition because you write your code
faster you write less code it's easier
to troubleshoot and we granteed will
scale infinitely if your company becomes
successful we had startups growing like
THX 10,000x within a few months on their
traffic and they just didn't need to
change a line of code we just kept like
just our Cloud was able to handle all
their load I'll put links for the
courses and other resources how about
what's next for temporal and temporal
Cloud I think we're looking at quarter
one of 2024 or into 2024 uh so a few big
things going on one is that we are
productizing this multi-region support I
mentioned we didn't have it in the cloud
working so it will be available
beginning next year so would we call
Global namespace so name space which is
distributed across multiple regions so
it will allow you to have very high
availability for your workloads the
other thing uh we still don't have
ability to sign up for our Cloud just
through sign up flow without just
passing your credit card information you
still need to kind of fill up the form
and we will send you email it's a little
bit more complicated if necessary so
beginning next year we will kind of
create fully self Ser pip line for
signing up accounts that is another big
thing and then other important project
we call Nexus it's a kind of new way to
think about because think about temporal
it's not just workflow temporal is a
service mesh for long running operations
because when you invoke an activity you
technically call a function in a block
in way right depending on your language
maybe it's a sync Block in but it's
maybe real Block in in Java and you this
function runs on remote machine so
you're technically Cor in RPC an RPC can
take 5 days it's a very powerful
Paradigm it makes life is developer much
simpler than think trying to model that
as a bunch of I think events and
temporal we want to make it very first
class citizen so pra will be able to
Define apis and every API would be able
to have like as could run as long as
necessary so we kind of have this notion
of arbitrary length operations operation
which can take any amount of time and
that will allow you to practically use
temporal as a service mesh to link all
services you Enterprise together and
don't rely on cues or events just
practically doing this long run in RPC
we call it project Nexus so I think
first version of that should should come
out beginning next year yeah it's really
interesting to see how things are
evolving and I think there's a lot of
potential yet to be tapped even so I'll
put all the links for these resources in
the show notes thank you for joining me
today Maxim thanks a lot for inviting me
it was pleasure this has been Philip
Winston for software engineering radio
thanks for
listening thanks for listening to SC
radio an educational program brought to
you by It software magazine for more
about the podcast including other
episodes visit our website at C-
radio.net to provide feedback you can
comment on each episode on the website
or reach us on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter
or through our slack Channel at
seo. slack.com you can also email us at
team-
radio.net this and all other episodes of
SC radio is licensed under creative
comments license
2.5 thanks for
[Music]